<P>When the MuteQuantMIDIStartSong command is received, the Loop is muted instantly and then waits until the next StartPoint. The display will show “St.S.” When it reaches the StartPoint a MIDI StartSong message is sent out the MIDI port to start up the sequencer and the Loop comes out of Mute. This is similarly useful for when the Echoplex is the clock master and we need to restart the sequencer. In this case, both the loop and the sequencer can be muted and brought back on together. MuteQuantMIDIStartSong works the same as the Mute-Multiply combination from the front panel when Sync is set to OuS, but provides a more direct access since it only requires a single command instead of the two button combination. Unlike the front panel function, MuteQuantMIDIStartSong works for any setting of the Sync parameter and can be executed at any time. This allows you to always have a way to send a StartSong message in sync with the loop StartPoint, even if the Echoplex is not the clock master. </P>

<P>MIDIReAlign ( source# + 38) </P>

<P>MIDIReAlign executes ReAlign with a single MIDI command. The loop is not muted prior to the ReAlignment. If Sync = In, the display shows “AL” until the Global StartPoint defined by the sequencer’s clock arrives, at which point the loop is retriggered automatically from its StartPoint. When Sync = Out, the loop is retriggered when a BrotherSync is received. </P>

<P id="LinkTarget_534">MIDIMuteReAlign (source# + 39) </P>

<P>MIDIMuteReAlign is exactly like using ReAlign from the front panel, except it directly does the function without requiring double button combinations. When the command is received, the loop is muted and “AL” appears on the display. If Sync = In, when the next Global StartPoint arrives the loop is retriggered back in time with the external sequencer. When Sync = OUS, the loop is retriggered when a BrotherSync is received. </P>

<P>BrotherSync and ReAlign </P>

<P>As shown in the tables above, ReAlign also works when BrotherSyncing two or more Echoplexes together. When one Echoplex has had it’s StartPoint shifted off from the other, ReAlign can bring them back together. Send a ReAlign command to one of the units and it will wait for a Sync with “AL” on the display. When the BrotherSync pulse comes from the other Echoplex, it will retrigger its loop so they are both back in alignment with each other. BrotherSync is usually done with Sync = Out, so ReAlign to BrotherSync is available there as shown in the table above. </P>

<P>There can be some confusion when De-Aligning and ReAligning to BrotherSync with more than two Echoplexes. If you have two Echoplexes in BrotherSync and shift one unit’s StartPoint away from the other, you will have them both sending pulses on the BrotherSync line at different times. Those two are able to tell which pulse is theirs and which is from the other unit, so they can stay in sync with each other just fine. They can be ReAligned later at the user’s command. However, if you try to add a third unit to the sync it will see the two different pulses coming and be unable to tell the correct loop StartPoint and loop length. It will not be able to SyncRecord to the others correctly. The best way to deal with this is to have the third unit record a loop in sync before having any of them shift their StartPoints. Then it will be in sync already and not have to worry about joining the sync later. Or ReAlign the other two first before the third unit joins. </P>

<P>An alternative would be to use the QuantStartPoint command on the unit that has been shifted, so that it will reset its StartPoint to the next BrotherSync coming in from the other Echoplex. Then they will both have their StartPoints in the same spot and be sending BrotherSync pulses at the same time so there will not be any confusion for the third unit. Of course this means ReAlign can no longer be used on the second machine to put it back in the original alignment with the first. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>StopSync </H3>

<P>If a sync has been received, pressing Overdub in Reset switches off reception of incoming Sync events. This is called StopSync. The Overdub LED turns red to indicate that sync reception is disabled. StopSync is useful if you want to disregard sync for the next Record. </P>

<P>Another Overdub press in reset or GeneralReset makes the Echoplex receptive to Sync again. This is called ContinueSync. The Overdub LED is turned off until the next sync comes. So after doing a Reset you continue in sync with the incoming clock, but with an Overdub in Reset you can then Record a new Cycle length, unrelated to the external clock. (This is mainly useful for working with other devices that send clock all the time, like Yamaha products.) </P>

<P>StopSync also disables Tempo, so you can temporarily escape from a Tempo you have defined and then return to it. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>SyncStartPoint </H3>

<P>Pressing Undo in Reset when Sync = In defines a new Global sync start point just like switching on a MIDI clock or sending a StartSong to the Echoplex does. The Global MIDI clock counter is also restarted at this point. Reset does not do this. </P>

<P>When it is pressed, we also send out a StartSong message. This allows you to have a clock source upstream of the Echoplex, and be able to stop a downstream device and restart it in alignment with the Echoplex StartPoint. </P>

<P>If the Echoplex is in a state where we are waiting for a sync, pressing Undo stops it from waiting so recording can be done normally. </P>

<P>SyncStartPoint is also useful when working with units that send clock all the time. (like Yamaha). </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3 id="LinkTarget_535">Tempo Select </H3>

<P>There is a new way to define the tempo of a loop in advance in BPM. This is done by pressing the Undo button in Reset to enter the Tempo Select state and then using the FeedBack knob to set the tempo before a loop is recorded. When this is done a MIDIclock can be sent out and a sequencer or drum machine can be started in tempo. Then a loop can be SyncRecorded to it so that everything matches the preset tempo. </P>

<P>For more details on the new Tempo Select feature see the description under the New Loop Functions section. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>StartSong, StopSong, and Continue </H3>

<P>A new value for the Sync parameter allows the user to select how MIDI StartSong and StopSong messages are sent when the Echoplex is the clock master. This choice can be very useful in different circumstances when controlling external sequencers. For example, some sequencers need to have the clock sent in advance to set the tempo, with the StartSong sent later. In other cases you may want to have the StartSong sent immediately with the MIDI clock when the loop is recorded so that a sequencer starts right up with the clock. </P>

<P>The possible Sync parameter settings are as follows: </P>

<P>Sync = Out – StartSong and StopSong messages are sent in most instances. MIDI clock is also sent based on the Cycle length of the loop and the setting of the 8th/Cycle parameter. </P>

<P>Sync = OutManualStartSong (OuS on the display) – MIDI clock is sent, but no StartSong or StopSong messages unless the user specifically commands it. </P>

<P>Sync = In – MIDI clock, StartSong, and StopSong messages are only received, not sent. They are piped through. </P>

<P>Sync = Off – MIDI clock, StartSong, and StopSong messages are neither sent or received. They are piped through. </P>

<P>The exception is for one situation where we send StopSong in both Out and OuS cases: When the clock is stopped at Reset we send a StopSong. This avoids the case of the sequencer or drum machine waking up in the middle of a pattern when the clock happens to get restarted again. </P>

<P>The following lists all cases where StartSong and StopSong messages are sent, depending on the state of the Sync parameter: </P>

<P>If Sync = Out </P>

<P>We send StartSong at: StopRecord (finishing a loop record) Start SyncRecord (in case we come from Tempo Select) SetTempo in Tempo Select UnroundedMultiply UnroundedInsert UnMute (if MuteMode = STA) Mute-Undo trigger (if MuteMode = Cnt) Next (if SamplerStyle = STA) ReAlign MuteReAlign MIDIReAlign MIDIMuteReAlign QuantMIDIStartSong (only at next loop start) MuteQuantMIDIStartSong (only at next loop start) StartPoint MIDI StartPoint Undo Record (only at next loop start) </P>

<P>We send StopSong at: Reset </P>

<P id="LinkTarget_536">GeneralReset Start Record Mute (if MuteMode=STA) </P>

<P>If Sync = OutManualStartSong (OuS) </P>

<P>We send StartSong at: QuantMIDIStartSong (only at next loop start) MuteQuantMIDIStartSong (only at next loop start) Mute-Mutliply ReAlign </P>

<P>We send StopSong at: Reset GeneralReset Start Record </P>

<P>If Sync = IN </P>

<P>We send StartSong at: Undo in Reset QuantMIDIStartSong (only at next loop start) MuteQuantMIDIStartSong (only at next loop start) </P>

<P>We send StopSong at: never </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Commanding a StartSong when Sync=In </H3>

<P>StartSong can be sent in Reset with a press of Undo. This can be useful if you have another source of sync upstream of the Echoplex, but have stopped something downstream from it. Pressing Undo on the Echoplex is a convenient way to send a StartSong message to the downstream device and start it up. This also restarts the internal clock counters used to keep track of the “beat 1” of the external sequencer. So if you get off from the sequencer somehow, or if you want to have a different point in the sequence considered as Beat one, tapping Undo lets you redefine the downbeat. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>QuantMIDIStartSong </H3>

<P>There is a new MIDI command &quot;Send MIDI StartSong at next loop start&quot;, or simply QuantMIDIStartSong. When this is executed, we send a MIDI StartSong message at the next StartPoint of the loop. The display shows &quot;St.S&quot; momentarily when QuantMIDIStartSong is executed. This command is very useful for restarting a sequencer or drum machine so it is in time with the loop. The function can be executed at any time, independent of the Sync parameter setting. QuantMIDIStartSong allows you to always have a way to send a StartSong message in sync with the loop StartPoint, even if the Echoplex is not the clock master. </P>

