<P>These become especially useful now with the new MIDI commands that can directly access so many functions. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Memory Size Display </H3>

<P>The size of the memory is only shown for a short time after startup and after GeneralReset. To see it again, just press Multiply in Reset. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H1 id="LinkTarget_529">Chapter 4:  New Parameter Settings </H1>

<Sect>
<H3>Loop/Delay Parameter Settings </H3>

<P>Changes to the Loop/Delay Parameter: </P>

<P>LoopMode LOP StutterMode Stu DelayMode dEL ExpertMode EXP InputMode In OutMode Out ReplaceMode rPL FlipMode FLI </P>

<P>See the New Functions Chapter for more details about these. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Quantize Parameter Settings </H3>

<P>Two new values are added for Quantize, Loop and 8th. </P>

<P>Quantize = Loop </P>

<P>This quantizes a function to the StartPoint of the entire loop, as opposed to quantizing to the next Cycle point if multiply or insert has been used. </P>

<P>Quantize = 8th </P>

<P>This quantizes functions to the subdivision of a Cycle, normally determined by the 8th/Cycle (or Beat) parameter and the loop length. The exception is when Sync=In and a MIDI clock is being received. MIDI clock specifically defines 8th notes, so the MIDI clock information is used for Quantizing to 8th notes in this case. If the loop is too short it does not quantize at all. This happens when the tempo is above 400 BPM, and similarly means no MIDIclock is generated and the Timing LED does not flash. See the LoopDividing section in the New Loop Functions chapter for more details. </P>

<P>Quantize = CYC </P>

<P>This is the same as what used to be Quantize = On. This is now the setting for quantizing functions to the next Cycle point. </P>

<P>Quantize = Off </P>

<P>Same as before, this means there is no quantizing and all functions are activated immediately. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>8ths/Cycle parameter (8ths/Beat on older units) </H3>

<P>The 8ths/Cycle parameter has new values, allowing you to have up to 256 8th notes in a Cycle. This gives a lot more flexibility for how the Echoplex synchronizes to external devices. </P>

<P>When editing, the most important values come first to make them easy to select: 8,4,2,6,12,16,32,64,128,256, then it goes on with 1,2,3...96. Note that with the new data wheel feature, the top of the knob range ends at 54 instead of 96. This was done because we found it was easier to set the more typical values when the knob resolution was limited a little bit. To reach the values between 54 and 96 you simply use the front panel button to continue incrementing the number in the usual way. A long-press while editing the Parameter returns you to the initial value of 8. </P>

<P id="LinkTarget_530">When a loop is playing and 8ths/Cycle is edited, the change of value is only activated at the first Loop Start after you come out of the Parameter editing state. See the Synchronization chapter for more details. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Sync </H3>

<P>Changes to the Sync Parameter: </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Value </TH>

<TH>Display </TH>

<TH>Description </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>Off </TD>

<TD>Off </TD>

<TD>no Sync </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>OutManualStartSong </TD>

<TD>OuS </TD>

<TD>sends Clock, but does not send StartSong at Record </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>SyncOut </TD>

<TD>Out </TD>

<TD>sends Clock plus StartSong and StopSong messages </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>SyncIn </TD>

<TD>In </TD>

<TD>receives Sync </TD>
</TR>
