</TR>

<TR>
<TD>0 </TD>

<TD>access current loop number. </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>1-16 </TD>

<TD>access corresponding loop number 1-16. (if you have that many loops) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>17-16383 </TD>

<TD>access current loop number. (&gt;999 are clipped to 999) </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>The current sample number is then set to this value. Sample numbers on the Echoplex range from 0 to 999. </P>

<P>Device ID </P>

<P>The device ID of the Echoplex can be changed while in Upload-mode. Press Multiply to see the device ID.  Press it again to start incrementing the value. The longer you press, the faster the value will be incremented. Broadcasting (device id=127) is implemented. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H1>Sample Dump User Manual </H1>

<Sect>
<H3>Sending a Dump(Dump-button) </H3>

<P>The Dump button in the MIDI (P3) parameters of the Echoplex is used to send a dump to another device. </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>You see a 'd' blinking, indicating that data is dumped. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Pressing the Parameter button while dumping aborts the transmission. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>The device ID is 1. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>The sample number is the same as the loop number. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3 id="LinkTarget_548">Sending &amp; Receiving (Upload-button) </H3>

<P>Press Load to enter the Upload-Mode. </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>You see a '-' blinking, indicating that the Echoplex waits for specific commands, which can come from the buttons or via MIDI. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>The Upload-mode allows much more than just uploading.  You can also send a dump from it or change sample dump parameters. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Button commands in Upload-mode </P>

<P>Parameter </P>

<P>Exits the Upload-mode. You will see the P3 display again. If you received a loop it may be stored in a loop other than the one that you are hearing now.  Leave the parameter mode and select the loop with the Next button. </P>

<P>Record </P>

<P>Changes current loop number. The default is the loop you where listening to. Maximaum range from 0 to 16 (depends on the number of loops). Ln is shown in the green display. </P>

<P>Multiply </P>

<P>Changes the device ID. The default is 1. Range from 0 to 127. 127 is used to broadcast to all </P>

<P>receivers/accept all senders. Id is shown in the green display. </P>

<P>Overdub </P>
