<LBody>Press Parameters on B to exit Upload-Mode </LBody>
</LI>

<LI id="LinkTarget_549">(B shows 'P3' again) </LI>
</L>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Echoplex B has now uploaded the loop. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Not all samplers or computer programs are capable of all of these possible protocols. Some implement only the open loop protocol, some require a closed loop and don't operate on an open loop. It is even possible that your sampler has no Dump button, but can still handle MIDI Sample Dump when the Echoplex is sending the appropriate commands via MIDI. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>How long will it take? </H3>

<P>Your SampleDump will probably take a long time. MIDI is slow and samples used in looping tend to be big. The exact time depends on how long the sample is and whether the receiving unit acknowledges the data packages or not (the Echoplex does). </P>

<P>Here are a few estimates for the open loop (no acknowledges): </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TD>Sample Length </TD>

<TD>Transmission Time </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>0.1 sec </TD>

<TD>9 sec </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>1.0 sec </TD>

<TD>1 min </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>10.0 sec </TD>

<TD>10 min </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>100.0 sec </TD>

<TD>1 hour 50 min </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>And here the closed loop (with acknowledges): </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TD>Sample Length </TD>

<TD>Transmission Time </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>0.1 sec </TD>

<TD>5 sec </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>1.0 sec </TD>

<TD>50 sec </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>10.0 sec </TD>

<TD>8 min </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>100.0 sec </TD>

<TD>1 hour 50 min </TD>
</TR>
</Table>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H1>The Other End </H1>

<Sect>
<H3>Echoplex </H3>

<P>Sending MIDI SampleDumps from one Echoplex to another one is simple. </P>

<P>If you are connecting two Echoplexes make sure they don't use the same MIDI channel and/or the MIDI parameter &quot;ControlSource&quot; is switched off on the sending machines (both machines in a closed loop). This is especially necessary now with the MIDI pipe feature when using closed loop, since any MIDI command received is immediately sent out again. If you forget this, the two machines will send every button you press back and forth to each other in an infinite loop. Unhook them and do one of the following: </P>
