<P>While the knob is being turned, the Tempo is displayed in BPM on the LoopTime display. Once you’ve stopped turning it for a moment, the resulting loop time is displayed in place of the BPM. The loop time depends on Tempo and the 8th/Cycle parameter. We assume that a beat is a quarter note, so at Tempo 120 BPM and 8th/Cycle=8, the Cycle time results in 2.0 seconds. If 8th/Cycle is 16, you get 4.0 seconds, and so on. </P>

<P>With the feedback knob the tempo is adjusted coarsely, in 2 BPM increments. The Insert and Mute buttons can be used to fine tune the tempo from there. Insert reduces the LoopTime (increase BPM) and Mute increases the LoopTime (reduces BPM). Each press changes the loop time by approximately 3 milliseconds. Fine tuning changes are not shown in BPM, it only changes while the LoopTime is displayed. Unfortunately, the LoopTime usually shows the time in 100ms resolution! So you might not be able to see anything change on the display as you fine tune the tempo, until you have changed it by 100ms. But you can hear it. Since the MIDI clock is being sent out during this time, any device following the clock will be slowly changing in tempo as it follows the fine tuning. </P>

<P>A long press of Undo clears the Tempo and exits from Tempo Select. </P>

<P>Differences Between Sync = Out and Sync = OuS </P>

<P>Tempo Select behaves slightly differently depending on whether the Sync parameter is set to Out or OuS. With Sync = Out, StartSong messages are sent when you start Recording or when you Set the tempo with Undo. When Sync = OuS, StartSong is only sent at user command with the press of Undo in the Tempo Select state, but not sent when you start or stop Recording. If you have recorded a loop without StartSong, you need to do one of the new Quantized StartSong functions to send a StartSong message. This can give you more freedom in controlling when the sequencer starts. </P>

<P>See the Synchronization chapter for more details on the differences between Out and OuS. Details on the Quantized StartSong functions can be found in the Synchronization chapter and in the MIDI chapter. </P>

<P>MIDIclock and StartSongs </P>

<P>MIDIclock is sent out immediately when you enter the Tempo state, but without a StartSong message. Some devices like to have MIDI clock in advance, and for some cases this allows you to get a feel for the rhythm. But to really start things, you need to send a StartSong message! </P>

<P>Recording in Tempo </P>

<P>There are three ways to send the StartSong and get things started: </P>

<P>1. Start up the sequencer before recording any loops </P>

<P>The first option for starting the sequencer is to start it in tempo before recording any loops. After you have entered Tempo Select and set the Tempo, press Undo again. This press of Undo sends a StartSong message to the sequencer and locks in your tempo. We call it SetTempo. The sequencer will receive the StartSong message and start playing at your tempo using the MIDI clock out from the Echoplex, and the Echoplex and sequencer will be aligned from then on. If you don’t like the tempo you can press Undo to set it again with the feedback knob or the fine tune buttons. This StartSong is sent if sync is OuS or Out. </P>

<P>If you are not using a pedal for feedback, make sure you set the feedback knob back to where you want it for feedback before recording! Since you have locked the tempo, changing the knob position at this point will not change tempo, only feedback. You may also find the new RecordMode=Safe parameter helpful here. </P>

<P>Whenever you are ready to record your loop, you can simply tap record to begin. You will actually do a SyncRecord. After the second press of record to end recording, the Echoplex will round off the recording to the next sync point as determined by your tempo. Your loop will end at exactly the right length and in time with the sequencer. </P>

<P id="LinkTarget_512">2. Start up the Sequencer as you begin Recording your Loop </P>

<P>The second option for starting the sequencer is to trigger it immediately as you start Recording. You can do this by pressing Record directly when the Undo LED is still red, right after you have dialed in the tempo. A StartSong message is sent, and the sequencer will start at the same instant as you start recording your loop. In this case the press of Record is the SetTempo moment. When you press Record again to finish, the Echoplex rounds off the recording to the correct loop time, same as before. For this to work you have to have Sync = Out. </P>

<P>3. Record a Loop and Start the Sequencer Later </P>

<P>The third option lets you Record a loop without starting up the sequencer. This requires the Sync parameter to be set to OuS. Set the tempo in the tempo state, and then record your loop to it as above. With OuS, the StartSong message is not sent out when Recording is started or stopped, so the Sequencer will not start up. When you are ready to start the sequencer, you need to send a StartSong message with the QuantStartSong command executed by pressing Mute and then Multiply while the loop is playing. At the next StartPoint of your loop a StartSong message will be sent automatically and your Sequencer will start. You can also use one of the MIDI StartSong commands which don’t necessarily require you to mute your loop first. More details about the quantized StartSong commands can be found in the Synchronization chapter and the MIDI chapter. </P>

<P>SetTempo and Presets </P>

<P>The SetTempo moment when the tempo is locked in is important. At SetTempo the tempo you have defined with the feedback knob is stored as a parameter value in memory. You can then save it as a preset and recall it again later. This allows you to have predefined tempos stored in different Presets and jump to them immediately. See the Presets section for more information on Presets. SetTempo also means that the tempo is remembered if you go out of tempo and then come back. For example, after SetTempo and while still in Reset you press Overdub to disable sync. At that point you can record a loop out of sync if you like. After reset, press Overdub again to re-enable sync, and then press Undo again to go back into the Tempo state. Your old tempo is still there! </P>

<P>Sync=In and Sync=Off </P>

<P>If Sync=IN, the Tempo Select function can not be selected. The Undo LED is actually orange, indicating an alternate function. In this case a different function is available, where StartSong can be sent in Reset with a press of Undo. See the Synchronization chapter for more details on this. </P>

<P>If Sync = Off, Tempo Select is not available and StartSong messages are not sent. The Undo LED is off. </P>

<P>Storing Tempo in Presets </P>

<P>Tempo can be saved in a Preset. Whenever you recall that preset it will immediately come up with that tempo. To do this, you simply save to a Preset while you have a tempo set, and it will be stored. See the Presets section for more information on how to save and recall presets. </P>

<P>When you recall a preset where no tempo has been set, it is just as if this feature did not exist at all. It comes up without any tempo and behaves normally. </P>

<P>When the Tempo state is activated with Undo, it first displays the tempo value in the preset currently loaded. </P>

<P>If there is no tempo saved in the current preset, it defaults to 120BPM. From then on, as soon as the Feedback knob is moved, the new values is activated. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>MultiIncrease </H3>

<P>Multiply now has a feature to aid in creating very long multiplies, called MultiIncrease. MultiIncrease is also useful when you know exactly how many multiples you want to do in advance. Instead of waiting until the end of the multiply to make the second button press, now you can immediately tap in as many Multiples as you want in the beginning of the multiplying. The Echoplex will automatically complete that many multiply Cycles for you. This same function is also available for Insert, however for simplicity we will just describe it in terms of Multiply. </P>

<P id="LinkTarget_513">MultiIncrease is very helpful for situations where you want to have a large number of multiples and you don’t want to wait to the very end to remember to press Multiply a second time. This way you can set up in advance how far it will multiply and let it go while you continue playing. MultiIncrease is in addition to the normal Multiply operation, so the traditional use is not affected. </P>

<P>How to Use MultiIncrease </P>

<P>Once you have started multiply, immediately tap the multiply button again to signal you want to end. The Echoplex begins Rounding off the multiply, just as it always has. During the Rounding period, continue tapping Multiply to increase the number of Cycles you want to add. The number of Cycles where Multiply will be stopped is briefly displayed as C&lt;number&gt; while you are tapping them. If you like, you can tap them in very quickly right from the beginning. Or, if you have had multiply going for a while, using MultiIncrease simply adds to the number of multiples you already have. </P>

<P>If you are tapping the Cycles in quickly, it is helpful to remember that the first tap of Multiply is just starting it. The second tap is where you start counting the total number of Cycles you will get. This can throw you off when you count the Multiply taps quickly, because you need to tap one extra time than the number of Cycles you want. So if you want 4 Cycles total, you need to tap five times. You might count it start – 1 – 2 – 3 – 4. </P>

<P>Example </P>

<P>-Record a loop. </P>

<P>-Tap Multiply 4 times and you get: Tap 1: Start Multiply Tap 2: Stop Multiply, begin Rounding Tap 3: MultiIncrease (Cycles = 2) Tap 4: MultiIncrease (Cycles = 3) </P>

<P>-You’ve set it to Multiply by 3 </P>

<P>-At the third Cycle, the multiply will stop automatically. </P>

<P>MultiIncrease with Quantize=Loop </P>

<P>When Quantize=Loop, MultiIncrease adds entire loops. For example, if the loop consisted of 4 Cycles, MultiIncrease counts C 8, C12, C16, etc. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>MoreLoops up to 16 </H3>

<P>There are 16 loops available now, instead of 9 as in LoopIII. On the Loop display the numbers above 9 are shown with letters, due to the lack of a leading 1. So they go 1, 2, 3…9, A, b, c, d, E, F, G. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>New SwitchQuantize Values </H3>

<P>SwitchQuantize has three new values that add quantizing to the loop and mix the idea of Confirm with the idea of Quantize. </P>

<P>Loop (SwitchQuant = LOP) </P>

<P>Jumps to the chosen loop at the next loop end. Useful when multiplies and inserts have been done. </P>

