<P>Also, the 8ths/Cycle parameter has new values, allowing you to have up to 256 8th notes in a Cycle. This gives a lot more flexibility for how the Echoplex synchronizes to external devices. </P>

<P>When editing, the most important values come first to make them easy to select: 8,4,2,6,12,16,32,64,128,256, then it goes on with 1,2,3...96. Note that with the new data wheel feature, the top of the knob range ends at 54 instead of 96. This was done because we found it was easier to set the more typical values when the knob resolution was limited a little bit. To reach the values between 54 and 96 you simply use the front panel button to continue incrementing the number in the usual way. A long-press while editing the Parameter returns you to the initial value of 8. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H1 id="LinkTarget_527">Chapter 3: Display </H1>

<P>The Display has been enhanced in a variety of ways to make operation easier and give more information to the user. </P>

<Sect>
<H3>Visual Tempo and Sync Guide </H3>

<P>It is often difficult in looping to feel the length of a loop before there are any good rhythmic clues recorded into it. This can make it frustrating to overdub new material that is intended to be in rhythm. To aid in this a new visual tempo guide has been added to help the user find the tempo. </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Timing LED: </TH>

<TH>blinks with the sub-Cycles (8th notes) defined by Parameter 8ths/Cycle and the global clock. </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Keys LED: </TH>

<TD>blinks at local Cycle StartPoints. </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>MIDI LED: </TH>

<TD>blinks with the local Loop StartPoint. (only shown if multiples established) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Multiple Right Dot: </TH>

<TD>Global MIDI StartPoint (1 of the sequencer). only shown if not aligned. </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Multiple Left Dot: </TH>

<TD>Sync correction happens, as follows: </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH/>

<TD>bright: </TD>

<TD>sync came early (jumps back almost the whole loop) this means the external sequencer was a little fast </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH/>

<TD>faint: </TD>

<TD>sync came late (jumps a little) this means the external sequencer was a little slow </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Loop Green Dot: </TH>

<TD>AutoUndo executed (loop was not changed that pass.) </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>When Sync = In and an external clock source is present, the Tempo LEDs will initially reflect the StartPoints defined by the external clock. </P>

<P>If the loop is shifted out of alignment with the external clock, the Tempo LEDs will then reflect our internal loop StartPoints. The Global MIDI StartPoint LED (lower right dot on the Multiple display) will then blink in time with the StartPoints of the external clock. This gives a visual indication of how the loops are aligned. When a ReAlign is done to bring them back together, the Global MIDI StartPoint LED stops blinking. </P>

<P>The LED for 8th note sub-cycles counts on 8th notes determined by the global clock. The cycle LED, on the other hand, blinks at the local StartPoints. If multiple loops are used and the loops are switched unquantized, it is possible to see these move out of alignment with each other. This can be a little disconcerting, but it can also be helpful as a reference of where the global clock is in relation to your cycle points as you switch loops. </P>

<P>If the tempo is above 400 BPM, the 8th note sub-cycle LED stops blinking since it becomes useless as a visual indicator at such speeds. This is also the point where MIDI clock is no longer sent for similar reasons. You can still make loops as short as you like. </P>

<P>The Multiple Left Dot showing the Sync correction can be useful for tuning the tempo on a sequencer to match with an existing loop on the Echoplex. By watching the frequency and intensity of this LED you can quickly speed or slow the tempo of the sequencer to match loop in the Echoplex, at which point the dot disappears. This technique allows you to start a loop without the sequencer, then start the sequencer and tune its tempo to match. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3 id="LinkTarget_528">SyncTime </H3>

<P>After the second Sync pulse is received, or a sync is established by MIDI clock, the resulting Cycle time is displayed on the LoopTime display. This only appears while in Reset. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Feedback and Continuous Controller Display </H3>

<P>Changes to FeedBack are displayed briefly on the LoopTime display while they are being changed. The value appears as a red number (0 -127) in place of the loop time. The display shows the change whether it is made by the front panel knob, foot pedal, or through MIDI. MIDI Loop volume control is displayed in the same way. This is very helpful in controlling these values, since it is often difficult to tell exactly what you have set when using a foot pedal. In the case of feedback you don’t know the result until the next repetition of the loop, which can be frustrating if you didn’t really set it where you wanted. The visual display makes this much easier to manage. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Command Display </H3>

<P>Several new functions that do not have their own obvious LED indicator are displayed briefly with some letters on the </P>

<P>red display. These are: rE Reverse Fd Forward H.SP HalfSpeed F.SP FullSpeed LOA Load Preset SAF Save Preset RES Revert Preset to default AL ReAlign St.S QuantMIDIStartSong S.Pt StartPoint sent cS.P QuantStartPoint S.Un Short Undo L.Un Long Undo </P>

