
<TR>
<TD>multiplying </TD>

<TD>Pedal </TD>

<TD>100% </TD>

<TD>Pedal </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>inserting </TD>

<TD>0 </TD>

<TD>100% </TD>

<TD>0 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>replacing </TD>

<TD>0 </TD>

<TD>100% </TD>

<TD>0 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>mute </TD>

<TD>100% </TD>

<TD>0 </TD>

<TD>0 </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>FlipMode (Loop/Delay = FLI, Pedal Only) </P>

<P>FlipMode is an unusual and interesting InterfaceMode, in that the pedal controls both Loop Input and Feedback simultaneously. The interesting thing is that Feedback on the pedal is reversed! When the pedal is all the way in the toe-up position, the Loop Input level is zero and the feedback is at 100%. When the pedal is all the way in the toe-down position, the loop input is at 100%, but the feedback goes to 0. In use this is like a Hold pedal, but with a more fluid action. Or you can think of the pedal as a “soft replace” since operating the pedal lets you smoothly crossfade a replacement section into your loop. </P>

<P>To get the hang of this InterfaceMode, use loops of about 1 second, keep the pedal in the toe-up position most of the time, and turn the front panel Feedback knob to zero. In Overdub the Feedback is taken from the front panel knob (reversed!), so once you've made an interesting loop by crossfading in Play, you can keep it by going to Overdub. You can then do overdubs onto it using the pedal to control the input volume. By setting the front panel feedback knob you can make 'Overdub' into a simple delay, which can be used as a contrast to the unusual crossfade effect. Multiply allows you to continue to crossfade over repetitions of your loop. Insert is a Single Cycle Multiply (as described under the StutterMode), so you can Overdub onto repeats of the next Cycle in the loop. (Remember you can hit Undo to end the Insert and not keep the stutters in the loop). Mute allows you to build up a crossfaded loop without hearing it and then bring it in at once. To record an ordinary loop in this InterfaceMode, put the pedal in the toe-down position and end Record with Overdub. This InterfaceMode does not exist without a Pedal connected. </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TD>State </TD>

<TD>Feedback (reversed) </TD>

<TD>Loop Input </TD>

<TD>Loop Output </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>playing </TD>

<TD>Pedal </TD>

<TD>Pedal </TD>

<TD>100% </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>overdubbing </TD>

<TD>Knob </TD>

<TD>Pedal </TD>

<TD>100% </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>substituting </TD>

<TD>0 </TD>

<TD>Pedal </TD>

<TD>100% </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>recording </TD>

<TD>NA </TD>

<TD>Pedal </TD>

<TD>0 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
