<P>- Reset (start a new loop with the StartPoint at MIDI beat 1) </P>

<P>-ReAlign (Restart the current loop at the next MIDI beat 1) </P>

<P>-MuteReAlign (same as ReAlign, but the loop is muted while waiting to ReAlign) </P>

<P>-QuantStartSong (stop the sequencer and restart it at next Loop StartPoint) </P>

<P>- MuteQuantMIDIStartSong (same as QuantStartSong but loop is muted while waiting) Each of those functions is available separately from DirectMIDI (in any state, not just Mute.) </P>

<P>From the front panel the traditional cross function Mute-Multiply offers some of those functions, depending on the Sync parameter and Sync events coming in to the Echoplex. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>ReAlign </H3>

<P>The new ReAlign Function </P>

<P>ReAlign allows the loop to be aligned again with an external loop or sequencer that it was in sync with, after it has been brought out of alignment by the use of functions like Reverse, Triggering, HalfSpeed, etc.  This is very useful to allow rhythmic variations by shifting loops to run out of phase with each other, and then perfectly recover to have them back in perfect sync. It is also very helpful when composing with a sequencer, where you frequently need to stop the sequencer and restart it. Being able to restart them in sync becomes necessary. ReAlign works when the Echoplex is the clock master or the clock slave. </P>

<P>ReAlign makes use of the Global-Local MIDIclock system noted above. The Echoplex uses that to keep track of the “Global StartPoint” defined by an external sync source and our “Local StartPoint” as they are split apart. ReAlign essentially gives you a variety of simple ways to bring them back together again. </P>

<P>Accessing ReAlign Functions from the Front Panel with Mute-Multiply </P>

<P>Mute-Multiply is the button combination to do ReAlign from the front panel. When using this combination, the loop is first put into Mute, and then the ReAlign is armed by pressing Multiply.  When the next Global StartPoint comes, the ReAlign is executed. (There are also several new MIDI commands for ReAlign, detailed below.) </P>

<P>What exactly happens at that point depends on the setting of the Sync parameter and whether or not we have clock. The Display will show what specifically happens, whether it is ReAligning our loop to an external sync, or sending out a StartSong to an external sequencer. A ReAlign of the local loop is displayed as “AL” and sending a StartSong is “St.S.”  The Multiply LED will be red during this waiting time, to indicate the ReAlign is armed. </P>

<P>If you want to cancel ReAlign after it is armed, another press of Multiply switches it off and we don’t wait for anything anymore. This is helpful if you find yourself stuck there with no sync coming. </P>

<P>Here are the different cases that can happen with the Mute-Multiply state and various sync conditions: </P>

<P>Sync=In: </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Sync Event </TH>

<TH>Function </TH>

<TH>Description </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>BeatSync </TD>

<TD>TriggerSample </TD>

<TD>The loop is triggered to play once from the start. Repeated pulses on BeatSync retrigger the loop for stuttering effects. (same as in LoopIII.) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>BrotherSync </TD>

<TD>MuteReAlign / No reaction </TD>

<TD>The loop is triggered out of Mute to play from the start and continue playing. This ReAligns the loop while BrotherSyncing to other Echoplexes. If a MIDI clock has been received BrotherSync is ignored. </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>Global MIDI StartPoint </TD>

<TD>MuteReAlign </TD>

<TD>If MIDI clock is already being received when Mute-Multiply is pressed, the Echoplex waits for the global MIDI StartPoint and then retriggers the loop out of Mute. </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>MIDI StartSong </TD>

<TD>MuteReAlign </TD>

<TD>If no MIDI clock is present and a MIDI StartSong is received, followed by MIDI clock, the loop triggers immediately from the start and continues playing in sync. </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>Local StartPoint </TD>

<TD>N/A </TD>

<TD>No reaction to Local StartPoint </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>Aurisis Research * PO Box 40200 * Berkeley, CA 94704-4200 * http://www.aurisis.com * info@aurisis.com </P>

<P>Sync=Out: </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Sync Event </TH>

<TH>Function </TH>

<TH>Description </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>BeatSync </TD>

