<P>With Substitute the original loop playback continues while you are playing the new material. On the next repetition, only the new audio will remain in the loop and the old portion will be removed. This helps keep the groove going while substituting and gives you something to play along to, as well as giving an overlap between the old portion and the new portion for continuity. Substitute is the same as if you were doing an Overdub with the feedback turned down to zero only during the Overdub. </P>

<P>Using Substitute </P>

<P>Substitute can be used in several ways: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>an Insert button press when InsertMode=Sub </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>a LongMultiply (less accurate, see below) </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>3. </Lbl>

<LBody>a Record-Insert combination when InsertMode=rhr. (formerly called Rehearse) </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>4. </Lbl>

<LBody>the Substitute VirtualMIDI button </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>5. </Lbl>

<LBody>the SUSSubstitute DirectMIDI command </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>As long as Substitute is active, all playing is repeated once. This can be useful to find the groove to start a loop. Just hold Substitute down as you play, and when you’ve played something you like let it go! </P>

<P>When Quantize is Off, Substitute is an instant function with Sustain action, same as Replace. This means it is active while the Insert button is pressed down and turns off when you release the button. </P>

<P>When Quantize is on, pressing Substitute down puts the Echoplex into the waiting state until the next Cycle point. Once the substitute starts, releasing it also goes into a waiting state until the next Cycle or loop StartPoint is reached. If you simply tap the Substitute button, it will be active for exactly one Cycle. </P>

<P>There is a problem when you try to use Substitute with the LongMultiply option. During the first 400ms until the switch action is detected as a long press, it’s treated like a Multiply. This means the old loop is still present for those 400ms, and only after that it mutes for the substitute. If you have quantize on you will not have this problem, since the long press can happen completely during the ooo waiting phase. When the Cycle point comes Substitute is started directly. </P>

<P>Advanced Use of Substitute </P>

<P>If a Feedback Pedal is connected and you are using some of the new InterfaceModes, Substitute has some extended functionality that makes it even more powerful. StutterMode and ReplaceMode have this capability. While the pedal continues to do Feedback during normal playing, the front panel Feedback knob controls the feedback just for the Substitute function. So you can have different settings for each! If you have the FeedBack knob all the way up, The existing audio is completely preserved as you are adding more. So it turns into Overdubbing. With the Feedback knob turned all the way down, the existing audio completely disappears on the next repetition, so it is the normal Substitute. In between is where it is interesting, because you can choose how much the level of the existing audio should decay each time you do an &quot;overdub&quot; with Substitute. In ReplaceMode the loop output level is also set to 100% during Substitute instead of being set by the Pedal as it is otherwise. See the section on the new InterfaceModes for more details. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>SyncRecord </H3>

<P>SyncRecord is a variation of Record that is done when a Sync of any type is being received and Quantize is off. Instead of always quantizing Record when a sync is coming in as was done in LoopIII, we now do a kind of “Multiply over nothing” for the unquantized case. This means SyncRecord starts immediately when you press Record, counts the Cycles on the green display, and rounds at the end to fit the loop time defined by the sync. SyncRecord gives freedom from quantization, while still allowing tight synchronization to an external clock source. </P>

<P id="LinkTarget_511">During Reset, the Overdub LED turns yellow to indicate that a Sync arrived. When the second Sync point arrives to define the loop length, the display shows the resulting Cycle time. Whenever the Overdub LED is yellow like this, the next Record press will be a SyncRecord. </P>

<P>With SyncRecord, you only need to have received the first sync event to begin Recording. As you are Recording, the Echoplex will continue watching the sync to determine what the right cycle times are. </P>

<P>SyncRecord does make one improvement when Quantize is on. In LoopIII, as a loop was recorded in sync the cycles would not be counted or differentiated. Now the Cycles are tracked and counted properly. This means that if the incoming clock defines a Cycle length of 2 seconds and you let Record continue to 8 seconds, you will see the multiple counter counting from 1 to 4. The Cycle boundaries will be set at 2.0 seconds. In LoopIII it would have just made a big 8 second cycle. This is especially useful now since the Quantize function can quantize to either the Cycle boundaries or the Loop StartPoint. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Tempo Select </H3>

<P>Tempo Select is a way to set up the tempo of a loop in Beats Per Minute (BPM) before you record it. Once you set the BPM, the basic loop length is determined by the 8ths/Cycle parameter. You can also think of this as setting the loop time ahead of recording the loop. </P>

<P>The tempo is set with the FeedBack knob or by MIDI.  While still in reset and before a loop is recorded, you enter the Tempo state with a press of the Undo button. From there you can set the Tempo. </P>

<P>After setting the tempo the loop can be recorded. When you press Record, the Echoplex actually does a SyncRecord to the clock tempo that has been set. (See the SyncRecord section above or in the Sync chapter for more details on SyncRecord). This allows you to start the Record at any time. When you press Record again to finish, it will continue to the precise loop time determined by your tempo and the 8ths/Cycle parameter, and end the Record automatically. </P>

<P>Once the tempo is set in the Tempo state, MIDI clock is sent out. This allows you to start a sequencer or drum machine in time with your loop length before you even record the loop! Or similarly, it allows you to start a sequencer at the exact time you start recording a loop, instead of when you finish it! Tempo Select gives you a lot more flexibility for working with sequencers and other synchable devices over what was possible with LoopIII. </P>

<P>How to Use Tempo Select </P>

<P>Tempo Select requires that the Sync Parameter be set to Out or OuS. When you have Sync set to Out or OuS, the Undo LED will be green in reset to indicate the Tempo function is available. </P>

<P>To select the Tempo, first press the Undo button in Reset. This will put you into the Tempo Select State. From there you will see the display change and you will have several different commands available from the front panel. </P>

<P>The Tempo Select Display </P>

<P>When you enter the Tempo State, the Undo LED will turn red and the BPM will appear on the LoopTime display. The tempo LEDs will begin flashing to the beat. You will also see that the Record LED is green and the Overdub, Insert, and Mute LEDs will be Orange to indicate they have special functions. </P>

<P>Tempo Select Commands Record – record a loop in tempo. It will automatically do a SyncRecord to the selected tempo. </P>

<P>Overdub – Press to disregard the Tempo without erasing it.  If you press it again later or reenter the Tempo Select function, the tempo returns. </P>

<P>Feedback Knob – sets the Tempo. </P>

<P>Insert and Mute – use to fine tune the tempo. </P>

<P>Short press of Undo – locks the tempo and triggers a StartSong message. </P>

<P>Long press of Undo – exits from the Tempo Select state and switches the feature off. Any time a tempo has been set, a Long Undo during reset will clear it. </P>

<P>Setting the Tempo </P>

<P>Select the tempo with the FeedBack knob. You can select a tempo between 26 and 278 BPM. Tempo can also be set by MIDI using the DataWheel continuous controller. (controller #6) </P>

