
<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Choose another MIDI channel on one of them. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Switch the MIDI parameter &quot;ControlSource&quot; on the sending machine to off. This is necessary for closed loop, and both must have ControlSource off. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Select another MIDI parameter &quot;Source #&quot; for one of them, so they send on another octave. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>SoundDesigner ® </H3>

<P>SoundDesigner subtracts 2 from the device ID number. </P>

<P>Echoplex -&gt; SoundDesigner </P>

<P>Sending samples from Echoplex to SoundDesigner. </P>

<P>SoundDesigner -&gt; Echoplex </P>

<P>SoundDesigner and the Echoplex do not agree on how to calculate the checksum. The Echoplex sends a NAK (=Not Acknowledge) after every data-package. Luckily SoundDesigner ignores all handshake messages and the Echoplex stores it anyway so you will end up with the correct sample in your Echoplex. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Alchemy ™ </H3>

<P>Alchemy™ needs to initiate sample dumps in both directions. </P>

<P>Alchemy™ actually sends the sample number off by one. When you ask for sample #5 it actually requests #4 from the Echoplex. </P>

<P>Echoplex -&gt; Alchemy™ </P>

<P>Go into Upload-mode on the Echoplex. Send a request from Alchemy (menu: Network: Get Sound). </P>

<P>Alchemy™ -&gt; Echoplex </P>

<P>Go into Upload-mode on the Echoplex. Start the dump from Alchemy™ (menu: Network: Put Sound) Make sure the sample length actually has the number of samples that you want to transmit. Sometimes Alchemy stores short sounds in huge files filling the end with zeroes. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>K2000 ™ </H3>

<P>The K2000™ reserves the samples 1-199 for ROM samples which can not be dumped or overwritten. </P>

<P>It automatically adds 200 to incoming samples with sample numbers &lt;200. </P>

<P>Sample number 0 writes an incoming sample to the first free place. </P>

<P>The K2000™ always adds 1 to the sample number. </P>

<P>You have to set the device ID (called Sysex ID) to the same as on the Echoplex. Setting it to 127 doesn’t do the standard behavior (accepting all IDs), so make sure they are equal on both units. </P>

<P>Echoplex -&gt; K2000™ </P>

<P>Start sending from the Echoplex at any time. Make sure the sample you write to is free. You need to go into the Edit Keymap to see your new sample.  It is probably best if you add a new Keymap with your new sample. </P>

<P>K2000 ™-&gt; Echoplex </P>

<P>Go into Upload-mode on the Echoplex. Select the right sample number and send a Request (Undo-button). You can also start the dump from the K2000™.  The function is well hidden in the sample editor. Press &lt;Dump&gt;. The Echoplex will ignore the sample number you send and store it in the loop number you defined in the Echoplex Upload-mode (Record-button). </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>E-MU e64™ </H3>

<P>The device ID of the E-MU™ is set to 127 and cannot be changed.  It therefore will always accept all samples, independent of your Device ID. </P>

<P>Echoplex -&gt; E-MU e64™ </P>

<P>The E-MU™ accepts dumps at any time.  Just start sending from the Echoplex. </P>

<P id="LinkTarget_550">E-MU e64™ -&gt; Echoplex </P>

<P>Send a Request from the Echoplex at any time. (faster) </P>

<P>or </P>

<P>Start the dump from the E-MU.  This is very slow! </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H1>Troubleshooting </H1>

<P>MIDI Sample Dump is a standard. But not all samplers implement this standard the same way. This can lead to problems. </P>

<Sect>
<H3>Display </H3>
