<TD>N/A </TD>

<TD>No reaction to BeatSync </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>BrotherSync </TD>

<TD>MuteReAlign </TD>

<TD>The loop is triggered out of Mute to play from the start and continue playing. This ReAligns the loop while BrotherSyncing to other Echoplexes. </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>Global MIDI StartPoint </TD>

<TD>N/A </TD>

<TD>MIDI clock input is ignored when Sync=Out </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>MIDI StartSong </TD>

<TD>N/A </TD>

<TD>MIDI StartSong input is ignored when Sync=Out </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>Local StartPoint </TD>

<TD>N/A </TD>

<TD>No reaction to Local StartPoint when Sync=Out </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>Sync=OutManualStartSong (OuS): </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Sync Event </TH>

<TH>Function </TH>

<TH>Description </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>BeatSync </TD>

<TD>N/A </TD>

<TD>No response to BeatSync </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>BrotherSync </TD>

<TD>N/A </TD>

<TD>No response to BrotherSync </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>Global MIDI StartPoint </TD>

<TD>N/A </TD>

<TD>MIDI clock input is ignored when Sync=OuS </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>MIDI StartSong </TD>

<TD>N/A </TD>

<TD>MIDI StartSong input is ignored when Sync=OuS </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>Local StartPoint </TD>

<TD>MuteQuantStartSong </TD>

<TD>A StartSong is sent at the next Loop StartPoint so the sequencer aligns to the Echoplex. The Loop comes out of Mute at the same time so both start together, in sync. </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>Accessing ReAlign Functions with MIDI </P>

<P>There are several new MIDI commands in support of ReAlign, which give us much more flexibility than we have from just the front panel. With MIDI the ReAlign commands can be accessed at any time with single button press, and don’t necessarily require going into Mute first. (See the MIDI commands section for more info on other new MIDI commands.) </P>

<P>QuantMIDIStartSong (source# + 40) </P>

<P>QuantMIDIStartSong waits until the next Loop StartPoint, and then sends a StartSong message out the MIDI port. The Loop continues playing the whole time, and “St.S” is displayed during the waiting period to indicate what is happening. QuantMIDIStartSong is useful when the Echoplex is the clock master and the external sequencer has been stopped. Now the sequencer can be restarted right in time with the loop. QuantMIDIStartSong can be executed at any time, independent of the Sync parameter setting. This allows you to always have a way to send a StartSong message in sync with the loop StartPoint, even if the Echoplex is not the clock master. </P>

<P>MuteQuantMIDIStartSong (source# + 41) </P>

