
<P>Chapter 9: SYSEX Control Detailed Documentation.....................................................61 </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H1 id="LinkTarget_508">Audience for the Upgrade Manual </H1>

<P>The LoopIV Upgrade Manual is intended for users who are upgrading their Echoplex from LoopIII to LoopIV. The intent is to explain the new features of LoopIV and how they work. It is assumed the reader is already familiar with existing functions and concepts from LoopIII, so they are generally not re-explained. You should refer to the LoopIII manual when you are unsure about an existing feature of Loop. In general, this is a reference manual and not an applications guide. </P>

<P>You may also wish to consult the Aurisis Research and Gibson Guitar Echoplex web sites for occasional manual updates and other useful information. at http://www.aurisis.com and http://www.gibsonechoplex.com. </P>

<P>Another good source of information is the Looper community at Looper’s Delight, http://www.loopers-delight.com. There you can find many other loopers and Echoplex users sharing tips and techniques. There is also an Echoplex FAQ and pages of tips from different users. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H1>New Feature Overview </H1>

<P>The following is a brief list of what is new about LoopIV. Please consult the following chapters for details about any given feature. </P>

<Sect>
<H3>New Functions and Features </H3>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Half Speed </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>SUS Commands – Real Time Granular Looping </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Substitute </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Feedback Display </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Tempo Select </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>SyncRecord </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Sync ReAlign </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>MultiIncrease </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Record-to-NextLoop </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>LoopWindowing </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>LoopDividing • 16 Loops </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>New InterfaceModes – Stutter, Expert, Input, Replace, Flip </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Parameter Presets </LBody>
</LI>
