<P>Normally, when the MoreLoops parameter is changed a General Reset is done automatically. This is necessary because the memory must be reorganized to support the new number of loops, but it unfortunately means current loops are lost. When you change MoreLoops from the front panel we assume you are doing it consciously and are aware that any loops you have going will get reset. However, we found it was very easy to change to a preset while you are playing without realizing that it had a different number of loops stored, and consequently destroy something you are playing. </P>

<P>We developed a simple system to protect against this situation. Whenever you change presets while in a loop with something recorded, any change in the MoreLoops parameter due to the Preset change is ignored. So your loops are not destroyed by the Preset change. If you are in a reset loop when you make the Preset change, we go ahead and implement the MoreLoops change as well and do the GeneralReset. If you changed the preset while playing and you really did want the MoreLoops to change and have everything reset, you will need to reset the current loop and then reload that preset. </P>

<P>Understanding the Playing State “Preset” </P>

<P>Preset 0 is the preset used and edited while playing. These are the Parameters active while you use the Echoplex. When one of the fifteen presets is loaded for use, what really happens is the values in that saved preset are copied into Preset 0 to be used while playing. When you save a preset using the preset editor, what really happens is the values in the Preset 0 playing state are copied into the preset you are saving to. </P>

<P>If you make a change in a parameter value while you are playing, it is only changed in Preset 0, and the Preset you loaded is not affected. This is really helpful because it means you can freely reach over and change something as you play, without affecting any Presets. When you decide you like a setup, you can then go into the Preset Editor and save it. Or you can load up another preset you have saved to get back to a known state. Changes made in Preset 0 are preserved when the power is turned off. </P>

<P>Preset 0 is really the same as the way Parameters worked in LoopIII. So if you do not use Presets at all, everything will be the same as it was before in LoopIII when you make Parameter changes. As you change Parameters, you will actually be editing the Preset 0 location, but you won’t even realize it. </P>

<P>We call the playing state “Preset 0” now because that is the actual location in memory where it lives. This will matter to you if you use Sysex or a preset librarian program to edit the parameter values saved in your presets. If you want to edit the active playing state parameters with Sysex, you simply edit the Preset 0 location. See the Sysex chapter for more information on Sysex control. </P>

<P>Selecting Presets from the Front Panel </P>

<P>In Reset, the Mute and Insert buttons can be used to select and load Presets 1 -15. Mute scrolls up and Insert scrolls down. The preset number is displayed on the LoopTime display as it is selected. Once you stop on one for longer than 400ms it will be loaded. The display briefly shows “LOA” when the preset loads. The Mute and Insert LEDs will be Orange to indicate they are available for preset selection. </P>

<P>There are two important things to note about the front panel preset selection feature. For one, if InsertMode = Half Speed you do not have the Insert button available to scroll down through the Presets. This is because we want to be able to start loops in half speed, so the Insert button is dedicated to selecting half speed while in reset. You will be able to tell this is the case because the Insert LED will be green or red (full speed and half speed, respectively). It is Orange if it is available for changing presets. You will also be able to tell if you press Insert anyway, because the display will show H.SP or F.SP instead of the preset number. </P>

<P>The second important thing to note is the front panel Preset selection is not available at all until you have saved your first preset! This was done to make the new user interface friendlier to new users. We didn’t want somebody to accidentally press the button, select a preset, and lose any other parameter changes they had made before they understood how the preset feature worked. So until they’ve read this section and learned how the presets work, we save them from that mistake. In any case, there is no point in loading presets if you haven’t saved any, so we don’t clutter the interface with it. </P>

<P id="LinkTarget_544">Selecting Presets with MIDI Program Change </P>

<P>Selecting presets with MIDI is very straight forward. MIDI program change messages 1 – 15 select presets 1 – 15. Remember, MoreLoops value changes are not made unless we are already in Reset. </P>

<P>If you have edited parameters on the fly and want to return to what you had, MIDI program change 16 reloads the original saved preset. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Preset Editor </H3>

<P>Accessing the Preset Editor </P>

<P>The Preset Editor is accessed by the “Reserved” parameter. This is in the “Switches” (or “Keys”) row, under the NextLoop Button. When you press it you are in the Editor for the Presets. There, all the other buttons get a new </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>function. </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Preset Editor Commands </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Mute </TH>

<TD>counts up Preset# </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Insert </TH>

<TD>counts down Preset# </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Multiply </TH>

<TD>Sets selected Preset and Preset 0 to factory default </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Overdub </TH>

<TD>long press saves the playing state settings (Preset 0) to the preset displayed </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Record </TH>

<TD>loads the preset displayed to the playing state setting (preset 0) for use. </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>Preset Editor Display </P>

<P>The Display shows the Preset number as “Pr  #”. No dot after “Pr” indicates that this Preset is the last one that has been loaded into the Playing state Preset 0. If there is a dot after “Pr”, it is not the one loaded. When the display shows “PrE” it means that the Preset 0 parameter settings have been modified since the preset was loaded to them. With the display indicators it should be easy to tell in the editor which preset you are currently using, and if there are new changes made that you may want to save. </P>

<P>Time Required for Saving Presets </P>

<P>Please note that the saving of a Preset to the non-volatile memory in the Echoplex takes about 400ms. if the unit is power cycled before that, it may come back on with different parameter values than expected. Make certain you wait a second after saving for the Parameters to be fully saved before turning off the power. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Sysex Dump/Load </H3>

<P>Parameter sets can be dumped and loaded from an external MIDI device for backups or librarian functions. See the Sysex section for more details. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Sysex Individual Parameter Editing </H3>

<P>All parameters can be individually edited by Sysex. Sysex editing is useful for backing up your settings and presets, sending song parameters from a sequencer, or controlling single parameters from a capable MIDI controller. Since the sound is interrupted during this edit, you may hear a pause for a longer sequence of Sysex commands. For a single parameter change the dropout is not audible. All Sysex information is piped so you can set two Echoplexes to different Device ID’s and set them up separately, even with a simple MIDI-In to MIDI-Out connection. Make certain you have set the Echoplex device ID to something. If the Device ID is left at 0, sysex will not be received. See the Sysex section for more details. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>DataWheel </H3>

